Guide to the Charles Mason Remey Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Charles Mason Remey papers
1891-1957
1939-1957
MS 413
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
8
The papers consist of his travel journals in Europe and Latin America as a teacher of the Bahá'i faith (1945-1948) and typescripts of family biographies and other aspects of the Remey family history. Included are compilations of the life and letters of Charles Mason, chief justice of Iowa, of George Collier Remey, rear admiral in the United States Navy, and of Mary Josephine Remey. Remey's architectural career is represented in an "Architectural design for a Bahá'i temple to be built upon Mt. Carmel in the Holy Land."
Remey, Charles Mason, 1874-1974
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Charles M. Remey, 1940-1958.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Charles Mason Remey Papers were given to Yale University Library by Mr. Remey. The family material consists of typed copies of manuscripts the originals of which are in other repositories, and Yale is one of several institutions that holds a set of these copies. It is not apparent whether any other institution has Remey's own travel diaries.
Biographical / Historical
Charles Mason Remey: studied architecture at Cornell, at École des Beaux Arts (Paris), 1896-1903; professor of architecture, George Washington University, 1908-1910; active in the Bahá'i faith and designer of the Bahá'i temple on Mount Carmel; author.
Bahai Faith; Families; Judges -- Iowa; Europe -- Description and travel; Iowa -- Politics and government; Latin America; Diaries; Architects; Clergy; Mason, Charles, 1804-1882; Remey, Charles Mason, 1874-1974; Remey, George Collier, 1841-1928; Remey, Gertrude Heim Klemm, 1888-1932; Remey, Mary Josephine Mason, 1845-1938; United States. Navy ( Biography)
- Inventory
  - A Teacher of the Baha'i Faith in South America--Diary of His Travels, 1945 November 10-1946 April 4 (Box 1)
  - "Journal Diary of Baha'i Travels in Latin America", 1946 December 18-1947 March 9 (Box 1)
  - "Journal Diary of Baha'i Travels in Europe"
    - 1947 May 24-Sep 21 (Box 1)
    - 1948 Apr 27-Nov 3 (Box 1)
  - "Houses in Which the Remey Family and Their Forebears Have Lived", 1957 (Box 1)
  - "A Record of the USS Remey, Assembled by CMR", undated (Box 1)
  - "Architectural Design for the Baha'i Temple to be Built upon Mt. Carmel in the Holy Land", undated (Box 1)
  - "Life and Letters of Charles Mason, Chief Justice of Iowa, 1804-82" [typescript], 1939
    - Volumes 1-7 (Box 1)
    - Volumes 8-12 (Box 2)
  - "Life and Letters of Rear Admiral George Collier Remey, United States Navy, 1841-1928," volumes 1-10 [typescript], 1939 (Box 2)
  - "Life and Letters of Mary Josephine Mason Remey, Wife of Rear Admiral George Collier Remey, Daughter of Chief Justice Charles Mason, 1848-1939," volumes 1-12 [typescript] (Box 3)
  - "The Wardrobe of Gertrude Heim Remey, 1888-1932" [typescript with photos], 1939 (Box 3)
  - The Lost Ring and Other Poems by Caroline M. Mason, 1891 (Box 3)
  - An Elementary Treatise on the Structure and Operations of the National and State Governments of the United States by Charles Mason, 1893 (Box 3)
  - Harriette Briggs Stoddard by Mrs. J. D. Kingsbury, undated (Box 3)
  - Reminiscences and Letters by Charles Mason Remey, 1910-1940s (Box 3)
    - Volumes 1-16 (Box 4)
    - Volumes 17-34 (Box 5)
    - Volumes 35-50 (Box 6)
    - Volumes 51-68 (Box 7)
    - Volumes 69-86 (Box 8)
    - Volumes 87-105 (Box 9)
    - Volumes 106-119 (Box 10)
  - "The Biography of a House: A Monograph of the Home of an Architect," by Charles Mason Remey, 1945 (Box 11)
  - "The Mausoleum of the Remey Family," by Charles Mason Remey, 1945 (Box 11)
  - Baha'i Reminiscences, Diary Letters, and Other Documents
    - "Daily Diaries of Charles Mason Remey" [thirteen notebooks], 1940-1948 (Box 11)
    - "Herbert's Diary: an Account of Trailer Travels Among Some Centers of Baha'i Teaching," by Herbert Smith, edited by Charles Mason Remey, 1949 (Box 11)
    - "Letters Treating of Baha'i Activities", 1920s-1940s, undated (Box 11)